## Dr. T. Everett Ellis

CONTACT Information 525 Madison Place SE Albuquerque, NM 87108 Phone: +1-512-814-8304 Email: t.everett.ellis@gmail.com

LinkedIn: teverettellis

SUMMARY OF QUALIFICATIONS

Computational scientist with a background in aerospace engineering and an emphasis on advanced numerical methods. Exposure to a variety of simulation domains including solid mechanics, electromagnetics, heat transfer, and plasma physics. Experience running commercial CFD/CAE solvers as well as developing research codes for a wide range of applications. Well developed programming and development skills (C++ and Python) with an affinity for clean, elegant solutions. Excellent spoken and written communication skills with a keen interest in project management and team dynamics.

Professional Experience

# Postdoctoral Scientist - Plasma Physics

2016 to present

Electromagnetic Theory Group, Sandia National Laboratory

- Took leadership of project management roles including running code review meetings and developing a hybrid Scrum/Kanban agile development process.
- Attended seminars, workshops, and classes on leadership, project management, and communication.
- Performed electromagnetic simulations of radar cross-sections using commercial and research software as part of a code verification study.
- Developed a highly scalable plasma physics code using the Trilinos Project.
- Contributed to a test harness for stochastic simulation codes using a new theory of stochastic Richardson extrapolation implemented in Python.
- Involvement with experimental analysis of electromagnetic pulses.

#### Graduate Research Assistant – Stabilized Finite Elements

2010 to 2016

Institute for Computational Engineering and Sciences,

University of Texas at Austin

- Organized and lead group meetings.
- Frequently presented research at national and international meetings.
- Developed space-time discontinuous Petrov-Galerkin finite element methods for fluid flow applications.
- Implemented a conservative formulation of DPG through Lagrange multipliers.
- Contributed significantly to Camellia, a parallel C++ library built on Trilinos for rapid development of DPG formulations.

# Graduate Student Researcher - Shock Hydrocodes

2008 to 2013

Institute for Scientific Computing Research,

Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory

- Took initiative in developing new features and research directions.
- Worked in a small research group developing advanced finite element discretization methods for Lagrangian hydrodynamics.
- Improved staggered grid hydro algorithms in multi-material Arbitrary Lagrangian Eulerian codes.
- Prototyped code in Matlab to explore the benefits of high order finite elements.
- Extended the C++ shock physics code Blast to axisymmetric problems.
- Developed a Python-scriptable plotting tool to interface with Blast.
- Implemented a smoothness indicator to isolate artificial viscosity to shocked and under-resolved flow regions.
- Contributed to open source MFEM finite element library.

**Undergraduate Student Researcher** – Shock Tube Experiments

Research Experience for Undergraduates, Aerospace Engineering,

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

- Designed a series of experiments and set up a lab to study the Mount St. Helens lateral blast.
- Developed CAD designs of experimental apparatus and assisted with assembly.
- Performed numerical predictions of experimental results.

#### EDUCATION

## The University of Texas, Austin

**GPA:** 3.92

Summer 2007

### Ph.D. Computational Science Engineering and Mathematics, April 2016

- Thesis Topic: Space-time Discontinuous Petrov-Galerkin Finite Elements for Transient Computational Fluid Dynamics
- Advisors: Leszek Demkowicz, Robert Moser

#### California Polytechnic State University, San Luis Obispo

**GPA:** 3.93

# M.S. Aerospace Engineering, June 2010

- Thesis Topic: High Order Finite Elements for Lagrangian Computational Fluid Dynamics
- Advisors: Tzanio Kolev, Robert Rieben, Faysal Kolkailah
- Summa cum Laude, With Highest Honors in Engineering

## B.S. Aerospace Engineering, June 2010

- Aeronautics specialization
- Summa cum Laude, With Highest Honors in Engineering

# REFEREED JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

#### T.E. Ellis, J. Chan, and L. Demkowicz (2016),

Robust DPG Methods for Transient Convection-Diffusion.

Lecture Notes in Computational Science and Engineering, doi:10.1007/978-3-319-41640-3\_6

·

T.E. Ellis, and L. Demkowicz (2014),

Locally Conservative Discontinuous Petrov-Galerkin Finite Elements for Fluid Problems.

Computers & Mathematics with Applications, doi:10.1016/j.camwa.2014.07.005

V. Dobrev, T.E. Ellis, Tz. Kolev and R. Rieben (2012),

High-order Curvilinear Finite Elements for Axisymmetric Lagrangian Hydrodynamics.

Computers & Fluids, doi:10.1016/j.compfluid.2012.06.004

V. Dobrev, T.E. Ellis, Tz. Kolev and R. Rieben (2011),

Curvilinear Finite Elements for Lagrangian Hydrodynamics.

International Journal for Numerical Methods in Fluids, doi:10.1002/fld.2366

## SOFTWARE SKILLS Computer Programming:

• C++, Python, Lua, MATLAB, Mathematica, and others

#### Scientific Computing Libraries:

• Trilinos, FEniCS, libMesh, MFEM, NumPy, SciPy, and others

#### CFD / Engineering Software:

• Fluent, Gambit, SolidWorks, Pro/ENGINEER, and others

# SELECTED CONFERENCES AND WORKSHOPS

- New Mexico EPSCoR Post-Doc Leadership Workshop, January 2017 – La Joya, NM
- Minimum Residual and Least Squares Finite Element Methods Workshop,
   November 2015 Delft, The Netherlands
- Minimum Residual and Least Squares Finite Element Methods Workshop, November 2013 – Austin, TX
- Advanced Numerical Methods in the Mathematical Sciences, May 2015 – College Station, TX
- Parallel CFD, May 2014 Trondheim, Norway
- MultiMaterial Hydrodynamics Conference, September 2013 San Francisco, CA
- U.S. National Congress on Computational Mechanics, July 2015 San Diego, CA
- U.S. National Congress on Computational Mechanics, July 2013 Raleigh, NC
- U.S. National Congress on Computational Mechanics, July 2011 Minneapolis, MN
- Finite Element Rodeo, February 2016 College Station, TX
- Finite Element Rodeo, February 2015 Dallas, TX
- Finite Element Rodeo, February 2014 Austin, TX
- Finite Element Rodeo, February 2013 Baton Rouge, LA
- Conference on Analysis of Partial Differential Equations,
   December 2013 Lake Buena Vista, FL

## Professional Development

- How to Effectively Mentor as a PI/Team Lead Sandia, 2017
- Agile for Research and Development Sandia, 2017
- Life of an Idea Sandia, 2017
- New Mexico EPSCoR Post-Doc Leadership Workshop Sandia, 2017

# AWARDS AND HONORS

- Awarded Computational Applied Math Fellowship UT Austin, 2010 2014
- Graduated Summa cum Laude Cal Poly, 2010
- Elected to President's Honors List Cal Poly, 2005 2007
- Elected to Dean's List Cal Poly, 2005 2008
- Litton Industries in Engineering Scholarship Cal Poly, 2007 2008
- Accenture Outstanding AERO Award Cal Poly, 2007
- Reinhold Aerospace Engineering Scholarship Cal Poly, 2007
- Elected to Dean's List Ventura College, 2002 2005
- Howe Heywood Mathematics Prize Ventura College, 2005
- James and Ida Iliff Memorial Scholarship Ventura College, 2005
- Alexis Dember Scholarship Ventura College, 2005
- Alpha Gamma Sigma Scholastic and Service Award Ventura College, 2003

## RESEARCH INTERESTS

Computational fluid dynamics, shock physics, multi-phase flows, turbulence modeling, finite element methods, Lagrangian hydrocodes, computational plasma dynamics, magnetohydrodynamics, computational mechanics